Guide to the Person Family Papers, 1754-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Person Family papers 1754-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Person family
6 linear feet Extent: 3000 Items
Family active in Louisburg, Franklin Co., N.C. and also in Nash Co., N.C. Correspondence, accounts, diary (1869), bills, deeds, wills, legal documents, and other papers (largely 1829-1897). The bulk of the collection relates to Thomas A. Person and his family, and includes letters written from Harrison Co., Tex., and New Orleans (ca. 1850s); student letters from various North Carolina schools (1835-1860); letters of Confederate soldiers concerning military life; and family and business letters with Civil War reminiscences. The early material mostly concerns Thomas A. Person's father, Presley Carter Person, of Louisburg, N.C., and the settlement of his estate. Later material concerns patent medicines manufactured by a member of the family. Other correspondents and names mentioned include W. P. Montgomery, Harriett Person Perry, Levin Perry, Theophilus Perry, Jesse H. H. Person, Joseph Arrington Person, M. P. Person, and Willie Mangum Person. Addition comprises primarily land deeds and surveys, other deeds of sale, receipts, personal wills, and other financial information. Also includes personal correspondence and memory books. An 1834 deed of gift to John W. Harris from P. C. Person includes five named slaves, one gray horse, 12 head of cattle, and 12 head of sheep. An 1808-1864 ledger book of Presley Person includes Person family genealogy and names and birth dates of his slaves and of the slaves owned by his son, Thomas A. Person. Other names mentioned include Matthew Culpepper, Arthur W. Person, Prudence Person, and W. M. Person.
RL.01016
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Person Family Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1944 and 2005.
Historical Note
Family active in Louisburg, Franklin Co., N.C. and also in Nash Co., N.C.
Genealogy List
1768 Nov. 13 Mary Person born
1774 July 28 Dr. Presley C. Person born
1807 Oct. 22 Dr. Presley C. Person and Mary Person married
1808 Oct. 8 Thomas Person born. Later married Abiah.
1809 Dec. 10 Lucy Person born
1811 July 7 Joshua Perry Person born
1812 Sept. 15 Mourning R. Person born
1814 Jan. 23 Joseph Abringham Person born
1815 May 15 Levin Person born
1817 April 21 Anthony Person born
1819 March 19 Weldon Edwards Person born
1820 Aug. 9 Presley C. Person born
1822 March 7 Willie A. Person born
1824 Feb. 28 Mary C. Person born
1826 June 3 Lucy Person died
1843 Mourning R. Person married John W. Harris
Dr. Presley C. Person and Mary Person's slaves and birth dates
1808 Champion(?)
1810 Hasy(?)
1811 Louis
1812 Mariah
1813 Harriet
1814 Clusey
1815 Thursney(?)
1816 Dick
1816 Nelson
1818 Isesy(?)
1818 Rachel
1819 Maple(?)
1820 Essex
1829 Seeley
1822 Henry
1822 Frederick
1823 Peter
1824 Burwell
1820 Anachile(?)
1825 Robert Hill
1825 Ellen
1825 Lucy
1826 Dice
1826 Isaac(?)
1827 Caroline
1827 Nancy
1828 Mariah
1828 Rosetta
1828 Matilda
1830 Rudy
1830 Ellick
1830 Cany Benton(?)
1830 Emily
1830 Ephrom
1830 Rebecca
1832 John
1832 Easter
1833 Emily
Thomas A. Person and wife Abiah's slave and birth dates
1832 Nash Pete
1834 Harriet
1835 Robin
1836 Iain
1836 Mal
1837 Roger
1837 Isham
1838 Alford
1838 Mill
1839 Selvy(?)
1839 Herrily
1840 Mariah
1840 Ann
1841 Iam
1842 Lucy
1842 Izabella
1843 Frank
1843 Fred
1844 Chany
1845 Bob
1845 Isaac
1846 Dun
1847 Daniel
1848 Sarrir
1847 Abner
1849 Osbun
1850 Green(?)
1850 Matilidy
1852 Dennis
1852 Cary
1854 Beck
1854 Amy
1854 Dick Dirt
1854 Delun
1856 Penny
1856 Arch
1857 Lewis
1857 Anderson
1859 Sallie
1854 John
1858 Dennis
1860 Beck
1860 Fred
1860 Ester
1861 Jef
1861 Ellick
1861 Alford
1862 Isham
1862 Morgin
1863 Mary Oliver
1863 Nancy
1863 Linny
1864 Lawrence
1864 Iad
1862 Isham(?)
Collection Overview
Correspondence, accounts, diary (1869), bills, deeds, wills, legal documents, and other papers (largely 1829-1897). The bulk of the collection relates to Thomas A. Person and his family, and includes letters written from Harrison Co., Tex., and New Orleans (ca. 1850s); student letters from various North Carolina schools (1835-1860); letters of Confederate soldiers concerning military life; and family and business letters with Civil War reminiscences. The early material mostly concerns Thomas A. Person's father, Presley Carter Person, of Louisburg, N.C., and the settlement of his estate. Later material concerns patent medicines manufactured by a member of the family. Other correspondents and names mentioned include W. P. Montgomery, Harriett Person Perry, Levin Perry, Theophilus Perry, Jesse H. H. Person, Joseph Arrington Person, M. P. Person, and Willie Mangum Person.
Addition (05-110) (200 items, 1.7 lin. ft.; dated 1754-1971 and undated) comprises primarily land deeds and surveys, other deeds of sale, receipts, personal wills, and other financial information. Also includes personal correspondence and memory books. An 1834 deed of gift to John W. Harris from P. C. Person includes five named slaves, one gray horse, 12 head of cattle, and 12 head of sheep. An 1808-1864 ledger book of Presley Person includes Person family genealogy and names and birth dates of his slaves and of the slaves owned by his son, Thomas A. Person. Other names mentioned include Matthew Culpepper, Arthur W. Person, Prudence Person, and W. M. Person.
Subject Headings
Person family; Person, Arthur W.; Person, Presley Carter, 1770-1845; Person, Thomas A.; Person, Prudence; Person, W.M.; Culpepper, Matthew; Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life; Education -- North Carolina; Patent medicines -- North Carolina; Soldiers -- Confederate States of America -- Correspondence; Students -- North Carolina; Slave records -- North Carolina; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate; Deeds; Wills; Receipts; Legal documents
Contents of Collection
- 1944 Accession, 1767-1910and undated, (5 boxes)
  Correspondence, accounts, diary (1869), bills, deeds, wills, legal documents, and other papers (largely 1829-1897). The bulk of the collection relates to Thomas A. Person and his family, and includes letters written from Harrison Co., Tex., and New Orleans (ca. 1850s); student letters from various North Carolina schools (1835-1860); letters of Confederate soldiers concerning military life; and family and business letters with Civil War reminiscences. The early material mostly concerns Thomas A. Person's father, Presley Carter Person, of Louisburg, N.C., and the settlement of his estate. Later material concerns patent medicines manufactured by a member of the family. Other correspondents and names mentioned include W. P. Montgomery, Harriett Person Perry, Levin Perry, Theophilus Perry, Jesse H. H. Person, Joseph Arrington Person, M. P. Person, and Willie Mangum Person.
  - Information folder (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1767-1863 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1864-1897 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1897-1915 (Box 3)
  - Financial papers, 1774-1863 (Box 3)
  - Financial papers, 1864-1914 (Box 4)
  - Undated papers (Box 4)
  - Financial volumes (Box 4)
  - Undated papers (Box 5)
- Accession (2005-0110), 1754-1971 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Addition (05-110) (200 items, 1.7 lin. ft.; dated 1754-1971 and undated) comprises primarily land deeds and surveys, other deeds of sale, receipts, personal wills, and other financial information. Also includes personal correspondence and memory books. An 1834 deed of gift to John W. Harris from P. C. Person includes five named slaves, one gray horse, 12 head of cattle, and 12 head of sheep. An 1808-1864 ledger book of Presley Person includes Person family genealogy and names and birth dates of his slaves and of the slaves owned by his son, Thomas A. Person. Other names mentioned include Matthew Culpepper, Arthur W. Person, Prudence Person, and W. M. Person.
  - 1754-1854, authorization from John Earl Granville of London to attorneys in N.C. (Box 1)
  - 1803, receipt from Matthew Culpepper to Dr. Isaac Hillard (Box 1)
  - 1805, 1817, fifteen pages prepared for court record of property acquired by grant or purchased over a period of time. Property located in Warren County, Franklin County, Halifax County, Raleigh, Fayetteville and the State of Tennessee (Box 1)
  - 1808, deed from John Culpepper to Osborne Culpepper (Box 1)
  - 1808-1864, ledger book of Dr. Presley C. Person, Franklin County Trustee. (Box 1)
  - Includes the listing of his marriage, his children’s birth dates, and names of his slaves with birth dates (all in back of book). (Box 1)
  - 1809, sale of lot 30 in town of Louisburg from John Perry to Jesse Person (Box 1)
  - 1812, Promisary note by John Ward to Matthew Culpepper (Box 1)
  - 1813, sale of lot 25 in town of Louisburg from Jeffrey’s to William Freeman, recorded in 1819 (Box 1)
  - 1814, license issued to Matthew Culpepper by state of N.C. to make distilled spirits for one month (Box 1)
  - 1814, payment of taxes by Matthew Culpepper (Box 1)
  - 1815, payment of taxes by Matthew Culpepper (Box 1)
  - 1816, payment of taxes by Matthew Culpepper (Box 1)
  - 1816, copy of C. Wright’s will (Box 1)
  - 1822, deed of trust for tracts of land sold by Sheriff Jordan Denson to take care of debts-foreclosure in Franklin County, North Carolina (Box 1)
  - 1825, list of town of Louisburg citizens paying corporation tax (Box 1)
  - 1825, list of people who have paid taxes in town of Louisburg (Box 1)
  - 1825, true copy-ordinance of town of Louisburg levying $1.00 poll tax and twenty cents on each $1.00 real property (Box 1)
  - 1827, list of taxables of Captain Darby (Box 1)
  - 1828, ordinance of town of Louisburg for poll tax and real property tax (Box 1)
  - 1828, deed from J.J. Alston to P.C. Person (Box 1)
  - 1828, deed between P.C. Person and Jesse Person (Box 1)
  - 1828, deed from J.J. Alston, Sr. to J.J. Alston, Jr. (Box 1)
  - 1829, Matthew Culpepper account for Jno. Arrington. Account paid in 1832 (Box 1)
  - 182?, Order of Court template letter-not addressed to anyone (Box 1)
  - 182?, valuation of town property in Louisburg (Box 1)
  - 1830, sale by Matthew Culpepper to Jno. Arrington for Brandy (Box 1)
  - 1831, bill from Matthew Culpepper to Jno. Arrington, Sr. (Box 1)
  - 1834, deed-gift to John W. Harris from P.C. Person consisting of 5 negros (named), one gray horse, 12 head of cattle, and 12 head of sheep (Box 1)
  - 1837, deed sale by Charles Johnston to Jesse Person (Box 1)
  - 1840, deed from Benjamin Davis and wife to Jesse Person and subsequent registration by William Whitfield (Box 1)
  - 1840, court order for Drury Andrew (also includes 1842, property of Ann Debnam to be sold to satisfy debt) (Box 1)
  - 1845, agreement between P.C. Person and Azariah Card for overseer job of his land (Box 1)
  - 1845, listing of property of P.C. Person (Box 1)
  - 1845, deed from Sheriff Guston Perry to Joseph A. Person and Weldon E. Person (Box 1)
  - 1845, affidavit from Sheriff of Franklin County that personal property of William Montgomery had been taken to satisfy debts. (Box 1)
  - 1846, reward of merit for Harriet E. Person (Box 1)
  - 1847, account of sale of personal property of P.C. Person (Box 1)
  - 1849, account of Thomas A. Person to J.G. King (Box 1)
  - [1851, book titled “The Element of Moral Science” written by Francis Wayland. Book was owned and signed by Harriet Person in 1853: removed from accession and cataloged separately.] (Box 1)
  - 1852, authorization to Thomas Person and others to hold pole for elections (Box 1)
  - 1853, personal letter from H. Person to his sister (Box 1)
  - 1853, memory book of Harriet E. Person (Box 1)
  - Needs conservation treatment before use. (Box 1)
  - 1858, notes of Joseph J. Davis relative to collections to be made for Sally Person (Box 1)
  - 1860, receipt from Louisburg Female College for the partially paid tuition of W.E. Person’s two daughters. (Box 1)
  - 1860, receipt from Louisburg Female College to W.E. Person for the tuition of his two daughters signed by C.C. Anderson (Box 1)
  - 1861, order from Elais Carr to Mr. Bartholomew ordering two blade saws and a boor (hog) (Box 1)
  - 1862, letter from Jesse H. Person to his mother during Civil War (Box 1)
  - 1863, resolution from camp near Culpepper, VA honoring the bravery and service of Jesse H. Person who was killed at Gettysburg (Box 1)
  - 1864, receipt from John Foster to Thomas Person for service rendered as overseer (Box 1)
  - 1864, portion of document by Confederate States of America as a receipt of twenty two hundred dollars from Mrs. Sarah Person for bonds (Box 1)
  - 1864, letter from A.P. Person to his brother about farming (Box 1)
  - 1865, private letter from Anna Person to her Uncle Tom (Box 1)
  - 1865, photocopy of parole issued to A.A. Person by USA for fighting in Civil War (Box 1)
  - 1866, note from C.H. Champion to T.A. Person about cutting hay (Box 1)
  - 1868, personal letter from Cousin Hattie to Cousin Harriet (Box 1)
  - 1893, personal letter from Aunt Tempie from Arthur Person (Box 1)
  - 1906, 1909, 1915, list of newspapers found in accession, but discarded (Box 1)
  - 1910, memory book of Marguerite Person from classmate at Louisburg College (Box 1)
  - 1911, several affidavits as to the ability of Mrs. P.J. Person to write her will (Box 1)
  - 1913, receipt for Mary Montgomery paid on note of W.P. Montgomery (Box 1)
  - 1914, order of Railroad Telegraphers card of J.H. Person (Box 1)
  - 1914, survey map of plat of A.W. Person’s residence lot (Box 1)
  - 1914, receipt of Mary Montgomery to satisfy judgment in Superior Court of Franklin County (Box 1)
  - 1917, letter from E.H. Malone (lawyer) to Mrs. Montgomery (Box 1)
  - 1917, resolution presented to General Assembly by Franklin County Ladies and passed re Veterans and flags (Box 2)
  - 1918, transfer of deed of trust from R.W. Hicks to Josephine Williams (additional notes added to the document in 1940) (Box 2)
  - 1918, promisary note by W.M. Person to W.M. Person to W.P. Montgomery (Box 2)
  - 1920, deed from W.M. Person and wife Prudence A. Person to A.W. Person (Box 2)
  - 1920, copy of will of Mrs. W.T. Montgomery (Box 2)
  - 1922, holograph will of Prudence A. Person (Box 2)
  - after 1923, booklet giving the “Argument of W.M. Person: The Crucifixion of Tax-payers of North Carolina” in the Supreme Court of N.C. (Box 2)
  - 1924, newspaper clipping re: Louisburg College Campaign, The Franklin Times (Box 2)
  - 1926, sale of property by A.W. Person (Box 2)
  - 192?, newspaper clipping on death of Judge Cook (Box 2)
  - 1931, personal checks of Arthur W. Person written on First National Bank which were returned to him because the First National Bank closed because of the Depression (Box 2)
  - 1933, invitation to Louisburg Female College Commencement Exercises (Box 2)
  - 1936, original and copy of title, mortgage, and other legal documents to land owned by A.W. Person and wife, Louisburg, Franklin County, N.C. (Box 2)
  - 1941, Office of N.C. Governor, Selective Service, appointing A.W. Person member of Draft Board for District No. 1 (Box 2)
  - 1948, map of lot in Franklin County, N.C. surveyed for A.W. Person (Box 2)
  - 1957, one share of stock in Green Hill Country Club purchased by A.W. Person (Box 2)
  - 1963, a State Magazine featuring Franklin County (Box 2)
  - 1971, aerial photocopy of farm from U.S. Department of Agriculture and letters on farm certification (Box 2)
  - Undated, valentine to Harriet Person (Box 2)
  - Undated, copy of Dr. William M. Person’s will (Box 2)
  - Undated, plat of land of Thomas Person (Box 2)
  - Undated, affidavit by Mrs. Joseph Blake as to the last will of William Montgomery (Box 2)
  - Undated, personal information about Thomas Person (Box 2)
  - Undated, provosts Marshall’s Office in Weldon, N.C. to Thomas Person thanking him for getting flour but unable to have delivered because of closed road (Box 2)
  - Undated, brochure relative to raising money to build Franklin Dormitory at Louisburg College (Box 2)
  - Undated, photograph of a man (Box 2)
  - Undated, newspaper article regarding the lynching of a Louisburg man (Box 2)
  - Undated, building information about a house built for Thomas A. Person called “Old Place of Louisburg” at 603 N. Main St. (Box 2)
  - Undated, newspaper clipping of photograph of Senator William Person (Box 2)
  - Undated, miscellaneous photographs of land (Box 2)
  - Undated, miscellaneous papers on loans and payments (Box 2)
  - Undated, miscellaneous receipts (four folders) (Box 2)
  - Undated, loose materials (Box 2)
  - 1886, diploma of Prudence Person from Louisburg Female College (Box 3)
  - 1887, Supreme Court certificate issued to William M. Person to practice law (Box 3)
  - 1889, sheet music by Mrs. Joe Person (Box 3)
  - 1911, certificate to Mrs. Wiley M. Person from the United Daughters of the (Box 3)
  - 1917, survey and, 1956, legal description, of A.W. Person Estate, Nash Co., N.C. (Box 3)